<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three to one being, an English-Spanish combat, performed by a westerne gentleman, of Tauystoke in Deuon shire with an English quarter-staffe, against three Spanish rapiers and poniards, at Sherries in Spaine, the fifteene day of Nouember, 1625. In the presence of dukes, condes, marquesses, and other great dons of Spaine, being the counsell of warre. The author of this booke, and actor in this encounter, Richard Peeeke [sic].</title>
            <author>Pike, Richard, fl. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855824</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 725:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three to one being, an English-Spanish combat, performed by a westerne gentleman, of Tauystoke in Deuon shire with an English quarter-staffe, against three Spanish rapiers and poniards, at Sherries in Spaine, the fifteene day of Nouember, 1625. In the presence of dukes, condes, marquesses, and other great dons of Spaine, being the counsell of warre. The author of this booke, and actor in this encounter, Richard Peeeke [sic].</title>
                  <author>Pike, Richard, fl. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Augustine Mathewes] for I[ohn] T[rundle],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Certaine verses, vvritten by a friend, in comendations of the author Richard Peeke", E2-3.</note>
                  <note>This edition has signatures: A-E⁴ (-A1, E4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Imprint cropped.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swordplay --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Three to One: Being, An Engliſh-Spaniſh Combat, Performed by a <hi>Weſterne</hi> Gentleman, of <hi>Tauyſtoke</hi> in <hi>Deuonſhire</hi> with an Engliſh Quarter-Staffe, againſt Three <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Rapiers and Poniards, at <hi>Sherries</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> The fifteene day of Nouember, 1625.</p>
            <p>In the Preſence of Dukes, Condes, Marqueſſes, and other Great Dons of <hi>Spaine,</hi> being the Counſell of Warre.</p>
            <p>The Author of this Booke, and Actor in this Encounter, <hi>Richard Peeeke.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GRATIOVS SOVERAIGNE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I were againe in <hi>Spaine,</hi> I ſhould thinke no happineſſe on Earth, ſo great, as to come into <hi>England,</hi> and at your Royall Feete, lay downe the Story of my Dangers, and Peregrination; Which I tell, as a late Sea-wrackt Man, (tos'd and beaten with many Miſfortunes;) Yet, ſetting my weary Body at laſt on a Bleſſed Shore: My Handes now lay hold vpon your Altar, which is to me a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: Heere I am ſafe in Harbor.</p>
            <p>That Pſalme of Kingly <hi>Dauid,</hi> which I ſung in my <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captiuity,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.</note> 
               <hi>(When as wee ſate in Babilon, &amp;c.)</hi> I now haue changed to an other
<pb facs="tcp:21327:3"/>
Tune; ſaying, (with the ſame Prophet, <hi>Great is thy Mercy towards me (O Lord,) for thou haſt deliuered my Soule from the loweſt Graue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 86.13.</note> And, as your Maieſty hath bene gratiouſly pleaſed, both to let your poore Soldier and Subiect, behold your Royall Perſon, and to heare him ſpeake in his rude Language; So, if your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, vouchſafe to caſt a Princely Eye on theſe his vnhandſome Papers; New Sun-beames ſhall ſpread ouer him, and put a Quickning Soule into that Boſome, which otherwiſe muſt want Life, for want of your Comfort. Thoſe Graces, from your Excellent Clemency, (already receiued) being ſuch, that I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſorry, not to haue Endur'd, and to haue done more in Forreigne Countries, for the Honor of Yours; When from ſo High a Throane, my Souereigne Deignes to looke Downe, on a Creature ſo vnworthy, whoſe Life, he proſtrates before your Highnes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Euer reſting, Your Maieſties moſt Humble and Loyall Subiect,</hi> RICHARD PEEKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:3"/>
            <head>Three to One: Being, An <hi>Engliſh-Spaniſh</hi> Combat.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ouing Countreymen;</hi> Not to weary you with long Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambles, vnneceſſary for you to reade, and troubleſome for me to ſet downe; I will come roundly to the matter; intreating you, not to caſt a malitious eye vpon my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor raſhly to condemne them, or to ſtagger in your Opinions of my performance, ſithence I am ready with my life to Iuſtify what I ſet downe; the Trueth of this Relation being War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rented by Noble Proofes, and Teſtimonies not to be queſtioned,</p>
            <p>I am a <hi>Weſterne Man, Deuonſhire</hi> my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and <hi>Taueſtoke</hi> my place of Habitation.</p>
            <p>I know not what the Court of a King meanes,
<pb facs="tcp:21327:4"/>
nor what the fine Phraſes of ſilken Courtiers are: A good Shippe I know, and a poore Cabbin, and the Language of a Cannon: And therefore, as my Breeding has bin Rough, (ſcorning Delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:) And my Preſent Being conſiſteth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the Soldier, (blunt, plaine, and vnpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed;) ſo muſt my Writings be, proceeding from fingers fitter for the Pike then the Pen: And ſo (kinde Countreymen) I pray receaue them.</p>
            <p>Neither ought you to expect better from me, becauſe I am but the Chronicler of my owne Story.</p>
            <p>After I had ſeene the Beginning and End of <hi>Argeires</hi> Voyage,<note place="margin">Argiers.</note> I came home, ſomewhat more acquainted with the World, but little amended in Eſtate; My Body more waſted and weather-beaten, but my Purſe neuer the fuller, nor my Pockets thicker lyned.</p>
            <p>Then, the Drumbe beating vp for a New Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, in which, many Noble Gentlemen, and Heroicall Spirits, were to venture their Honors, Liues, and Fortunes: Cables could not hold me, for away I would, and along I vowed to goe, and did ſo.</p>
            <p>The Diſſigne opening it ſelfe at Sea for <hi>Cales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cales.</note> proude I was to be imployed There, where ſo many Gallants, and Engliſh Worthies, did by their Examples, encourage the Common Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Honorable Darings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:4"/>The Shippe I went in, was called <hi>The Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> (one of the Nauy Royall:) The Captaine, <hi>Thomas Portar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the two and twentie day of October,<note place="margin">October 22. The Fleete came to <hi>Cales.</hi>
               </note> being Saterday, 1625. our Fleete came into <hi>Cales,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three of the clock in the afternoone, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all, ſome hundred and ten Sayle.</p>
            <p>The Saturday-night, ſome ſixteene Sayle of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and about ten <hi>White-Hall-Men</hi> (who in <hi>England</hi> are called <hi>Colliers</hi>) were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to fight againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Puntall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fight at <hi>Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi>
               </note> ſtanding three miles from <hi>Cales,</hi> who did ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and diſcharged (in that Seruice) at the leaſt one thouſand ſixe hundred Shott.</p>
            <p>On the Sunday morning following, the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> going vp very early,<note place="margin">Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi>
               </note> and an hower at leaſt before vs to the Fight, commanded our Shippe (the <hi>Conuertine,</hi> being of his Squadron) to follow him: The Caſtle playing hard and hotly vpon his Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Portar,</hi> and the Maiſter of our Ship,<note place="margin">Captaine <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi>
               </note> (whoſe name is M. <hi>Hill,</hi>) hauing vpon ſight of ſo fierce an Encounter, an equall deſire to doe ſomething worthy themſelues, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, came vp ſo cloſe to the Caſtle, as poſſibly Men in ſuch a danger either could, or durſt aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and there fought brauely: The Caſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing vpon vs a hotte ſalutation (and well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming our approach) with Bullets; whoſe firſt Shot killd three of our Men, paſſing through
<pb facs="tcp:21327:5"/>
and through our Shippe, the ſecond killd foure, and the third two more at leaſt, with great ſpoile and battery to our Shippe: The laſt Shotte fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo cloſe by Captaine <hi>Portar,</hi> that with the winde of the Bullet, his very Hands had almoſt loſt the Sence of feeling, being ſtruck into a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine numbneſſe.</p>
            <p>Vpon this, Captaine <hi>Portar</hi> perceiuing the danger wee, and our Shippe were in, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a number of vs to get vpon the vpper Deck, and with our Small Shotte to try if we could force the Cannoneers from their Ordnance.</p>
            <p>Wee preſently aduaunced our ſelues, fell cloſe to our worke, and plyed them with Pellets; in which hotte and dangerous Seruice, one Maſter <hi>William Iewell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>William Iewell,</hi> his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> behaued himſelfe both Manly and like a Noble Soldier, expreſſing much Valour, abillity of Body, and readineſſe; with whom, and ſome few more, I (amongſt the reſt) ſtood the brunt, which continued about three houres.</p>
            <p>Out Ship lay all this while with her Star-bord ſide to the Fort, who beating vs continually, with at leaſt two hundred Muskets, whoſe Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets flew ſo thick, that our Shrowdes were torne in peices, and our Tacklings rent to nothing; and when ſhe came off,<note place="margin">500. Bullets in the Star-board ſide of our Shippe.</note> there were to be ſeene fiue hundred Bullets (at the leaſt) ſticking in her ſide: I, for my part (without vaine glory be it ſpoken) diſcharging at this time, ſome threeſcore and ten Shotte, as they recounted to me who charged my
<pb facs="tcp:21327:5"/>
Peeces for me.</p>
            <p>In the heate of this Fight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> William Sentliger.</note> Sir <hi>William Sent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger</hi> (whether cald vp by my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or comming of himſelfe, I know not) ſeeing vs ſo hardly beſett, and that we had but few Shotte vpon our Deck, in regard of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies number, which played vpon vs, came with a Valient and Noble Reſolution, out of another Shippe into ours, bringing ſome fortie Soldiers with him, who there with vs, renued a ſecond Fight, as hotte, or hotter then the former: Where in this Fight, one of our Bullets was ſhotte into the mouth of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cannon, where it ſticketh faſt, and putteth that Roarer to ſilence.</p>
            <p>Vpon this Brauery, they of the Fort began to waxe calmer, and cooler: And in the ende, moſt part of their Gunners being ſlayne, gaue ouer ſhooting, but yeilded not the Fort vntill night.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this Skirmiſh continued, a company of <hi>Spaniards</hi> within the Caſtle, by the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a Wall, whoſe end ietting out, they ſtill as they diſcharged, retired behinde it, ſauing themſelues, and extreamely annoying vs; I remooued into the Fore-Caſtle of our Shippe, and ſo plyed them with Haile-ſhotte, that they forſooke their ſtand.</p>
            <p>What Men on our part were loſt (by their Small Shotte) I can not well remember, but
<pb facs="tcp:21327:6"/>
ſure I am, not very many: Yet the <hi>Spaniards</hi> afterwards, before the Gouernour of <hi>Cales,</hi> confeſt they loſt about fifty,<note place="margin">50 Spaniards ſlayne.</note> whoſe Muskets they caſt into a Well, becauſe our Men ſhould not vſe them, throwing the dead Bodies in after.</p>
            <p>My Hurts and Bruiſes here receiued, albeit they were neither many, nor dangerous, yet were they ſuch, that when the Fight was don, many Gentlemen in our Shippe for my encouragement, gaue me Money.</p>
            <p>During this Battaile, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>White-Hall-Men,</hi> you muſt thinke, were not idle, for their Great Peices went off continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, from ſuch of their Shippes as could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently diſcharge, becauſe our Shippe lay betweene them and the Fort; and they ſo cloſely plyed their worke, that at this Battery were diſcharged from the Ordnance,<note place="margin">4000 Bullets at the Battry of the Fort.</note> at leaſt foure thouſand Bullets.</p>
            <p>The Caſtle being thus quieted, (though as yet not yeilded) the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> about twelue at noone,<note place="margin">Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Regiment Landed.</note> landed his Regiment cloſe by the Fort, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> looking ouer the Walles to behold them: Vpon ſight of which, many of thoſe within the Caſtle (to the number of ſixe ſcore) ran away;<note place="margin">Spaniards ran from the Caſtle,</note> wee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing them with ſhowtes, hollawings, and lowde noiſes, and now and then a Peice of Ordnance ouertooke ſome of the <hi>Spaniſh
<pb facs="tcp:21327:6"/>
Hares,</hi> and ſtayed them from running farder.</p>
            <p>Part of our Men being thus landed, they marched vp not aboue a flight ſhotte off, and there reſted themſelues. Then about ſixe at night the Caſtle yeilded, vpon compoſition,<note place="margin">Caſtle of <hi>Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> yelded,</note> to depart with their Armes, and Collours flying, and no Man to offend them; which was performed accordingly.</p>
            <p>The Captaine of the Fort, his name was <hi>Don Franciſco Buſtamante,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Buſtamante,</hi> and his Men put ouer to <hi>Port Reall.</hi>
               </note> who preſently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deliuery, was carried aboard the Lord Generalls Shippe, where he had a Soldierly Welcome; And the next day, He, and all his Company were put ouer to <hi>Port Reall,</hi> vpon the mayne Land becauſe they ſhould not goe to <hi>Cales,</hi> which is an Iland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monday. October</hi> 24. On the Monday,<note place="margin">On Monday all our Forces Landed.</note> hauing begun early in the morning, all our Forces, about noone were landed, and preſently marched vp to a Bridge, betweene <hi>Puntall</hi> and <hi>Cales;</hi> In going vp to which, ſome of our Men were vnfortunately and vnmanly ſurpriſed, and before they knew their owne danger, had there their Throates cutte; Some hauing their Braines beaten out with the ſtockes of Muskets; others, their Noſes ſl e'd off; whilſt ſome Heads were ſpurned vp &amp; downe the Streets
<pb facs="tcp:21327:7"/>
like Footeballs, and ſome Eares worne in ſcorne in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hattes: For when I was in Priſon in <hi>Cales,</hi> (whether ſome of theſe <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Picaroes</hi> were brought in for flying from the Caſtle,) I was an eye witneſſe, of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mens Eares worne in that deſpightfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>What the Forces being on Shore did, or how farre they went vp, I can not tell, for I was no Land-Soldier, and therefore all that while kept aboard: Yet about twelue of the clock, when they were marched out of ſight, I (knowing that other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men had don the like the very ſame day,) ventered on Shore likewiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Richard Peeke</hi> on Shore.</note> to refreſh my ſelfe, with my Sword only by my ſide, becauſe, I thought the late ſtormes had beaten all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in, and therefore feared no danger.</p>
            <p>On, therefore, I ſoftly walked, viewing the deſolation of ſuch a Place, for I ſaw no body: Yet farre had I not gon from the Shore, but ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men were come euen almoſt to our Shippes, and from certaine Gardens had brought with them many Oranges and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>The ſight of theſe, ſharpned my ſtomach the more to goe on, becauſe I had a deſire to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſome of thoſe Fruites to my Captaine. Hereupon, I demanded of them, what danger there was in going? They ſayd, None, but
<pb facs="tcp:21327:7"/>
that all was huſht, and not a <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſtirring.</p>
            <p>We parted, they to the Shippes, I forward: And before I had reached a mile, I found (for all their talking, of no danger) Three <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Men ſtarke dead, being ſlayne, lying in the way, it being full of deepe Sandy pittes, ſo that I could hardly finde the paſſage, and one, ſome ſmall diſtance from them, not fully dead.</p>
            <p>The groanes which he vttered, led me to him; and finding him lying on his belly, I called to him, and turning him on his back, ſaw his woundes, and ſayd; Brother, what Villaine has done this miſcheife to thee? He lamented in ſighes and dolefull lookes, and caſting vp his eyes to Heauen, but could not ſpeake. I then reſolued (and was about it) for Chriſtian Charities ſake; and for Countries ſake, to haue carried him on my back to our Shippes, farre off though they lay, and there (if by any poſſible meanes it could haue bin done,) to haue recouered him.</p>
            <p>But my good intents were preuented; For on a ſodaine, came ruſhing in vpon me, a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi>-Horſeman, whoſe Name, as afterward I was informed, was <hi>Don Iuan of Cales,</hi> a Knight; I ſeeing him make ſpeedily and fiercely at me, with his drawne weapon, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly whip'd out mine, wrapping my Cloake about mine Arme: Fiue or ſixe Skirmiſhes
<pb facs="tcp:21327:8"/>
wee had, and for a pretty while, fought off and on.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and an Engliſh Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note>At laſt, I getting with much adoe, to the top of a ſandy Hillock, the Horſeman nimbly followed vp after; By good Fortune to me, (though bad to himſelfe) he had no Petronell or Piſtolls about him; and therefore clapping Spurres to his Horſe ſides, his intent, as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, was, with full careere to ride ouer me, and trample me vnder his Horſes feete: But a Prouidence greater then his Fury, was my Guard.</p>
            <p>Time was it for me to looke about warily, and to lay about luſtely, to defend a poore Life ſo hardly diſtreſſed: As therefore his Horſe was violently breaking in vpon me, I ſtruck him into the eyes, with a flappe of my Cloake; vpon which, turning ſideward, I tooke my aduantage, and as redily as I could, ſtepping in, it pleaſed God, that I ſhould pluck my Enemy downe,<note place="margin">The Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and haue him at my Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for Life, which notwithſtanding, I gaue him; He falling on his knees, and crying out in <hi>French</hi> to me: <hi>Pardone moy le vous pree, le ſuis vn buon Chreſtien.</hi> Pardon me Sir, I am a good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>I, ſeeing him braue, and hauing a Soldiers minde to Rifle him, I ſearched for Iewels, but found, onely fiue Peices of Eight about him, in all amounting to twenty Shillings Engliſh:
<pb facs="tcp:21327:8"/>
Yet he had Gold, but that I could not come by; For, I was in haſt to haue ſent his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Knight-hood home on Foote, and to haue taught his Horſe an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pace.</p>
            <p>Thus farre, my Voyage for Oranges ſped well, but in the end, prooued ſower Sawce to me. And it is harder to keepe a Victory, then to obteyne; So, heere it fell out with mine.</p>
            <p>For, fourteene <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Muskatiers, ſpying me ſo buſy about one of their Countrey-men, bent all the Mouthes of their Peeces to kill me, which they could not well doe, without endangering this <hi>Don Iohns</hi> life; ſo that I was inforced (and glad I ſcap'd ſo too) to yeild my ſelfe their Priſoner.</p>
            <p>True Valour (I ſee) goes not alwaies in good Cloathes; For, He whom before I had ſurprized, ſeeing me faſt in the ſnare, and (as the euent prooued) diſdaining that his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men ſhould report him ſo diſhonored, moſt baſely, (when my handes were in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bound behind me) drew out his Weapon, (which the reſt had taken from me, to giue him) and wounded me through the Face,<note place="margin">An vngentle vnworthy baſe <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </note> from Eare to Eare, and had there killd me, had not the foureteene Muskatiers reſcued me from his Rage.</p>
            <p>Vpon this, I was led in Triumph, into the Towne of <hi>Cales:</hi> An Owle not more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and hooted at, a Dog not more curſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:9"/>In my beeing ledde thus along the Streets, A <hi>Flemming</hi> ſpying me,<note place="margin">Wounded baſely by a <hi>Flemming.</hi>
               </note> cryed out alowde; Whither doe you leade this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dogge? Kill him, kill him, hee's no Chriſtian. And with that, breaking through the Crowde, in vpon thoſe who held mee, ranne me into the Body with a Halbeit, at the Reynes of my Backe, at the leaſt foure inches.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Noble <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard.</hi>
               </note>One <hi>Don Fernando,</hi> an antient Gentleman, was ſent downe this Summer, from the King at <hi>Madrill,</hi> with Soldiers; But before our Fleete came, the Soldiers were diſcharged; They of <hi>Cales,</hi> neuer ſuſpecting that we meant to put in there.</p>
            <p>Before him, was I brought to be examined, yet few, or no queſtions at all, were demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of me becauſe, he ſaw I was all bloudy in my Cloathes, and ſo wounded in my Face and Iawes, that I could hardly ſpeake: I was therefore committed preſently to Priſon, where I lay eighteene dayes: The Noble Gentleman, giuing expreſſe charge, that the beſt Surgeons ſhould be ſent for, leaſt, being ſo baſely hurt and handled by Cowards, I ſhould be demanded at his hands.</p>
            <p>I being thus taken on the Monday, when I went on Shore,<note place="margin">The Fleetes departure.</note> the Heere departed the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, from <hi>Cales,</hi> at the ſame time when I was there a Priſoner.</p>
            <p>Yet, thus honeſtly was I vſed by my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="tcp:21327:9"/>
Friend Captaine <hi>Portar;</hi> He aboue my deſeruing, complayning, that he feared he had loſt ſuch a Man:<note place="margin">The Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls loue.</note> My Lord Generall (by the ſolicitation of Maſter <hi>Iohn Glanuile,</hi> Secretary to the Fleete) ſent three Men on Shore, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in <hi>Cales</hi> for me, and to offer (if I were taken) any reaſonable Ranſome: But the Towne, thinking me a better Prize then (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) I was, denyed me, and would not part from me.</p>
            <p>Then came a Command to the <hi>Teniente,</hi> or Gouernor of <hi>Cales,</hi> to haue me ſent to <hi>Sherrys,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Xerez,</hi>) lying three Leagues from <hi>Cales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wondrous vnwilling (could I otherwiſe haue choſen) was I to goe to <hi>Sherry,</hi> becauſe, I feared I ſhould then be put to Tortures.</p>
            <p>Hauing therefore a Young man, (an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Man, and a Merchant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Goodrow</hi> a Merchant, <hi>Pikes</hi> Fellow Priſoner in <hi>Cales.</hi>
               </note> whoſe Name was <hi>Goodrow,</hi>) my fellow Priſoner, who lay there for Debt: and ſo I thinking there was no way with me but one; (That I muſt bo ſent pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to my long home,) Thus I ſpake vnto him.</p>
            <p>Countrey-man, what my Name is, our Partnerſhip in Miſery hath made you know; And with it, know that I am a <hi>Deuonſhire</hi>-Man borne, and <hi>Taueſtock</hi> the place of my once-abiding. I beſeech you, if God euer ſend you Liberty, and that you ſaile into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:10"/>
take that Countrey in your way; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to my Wife and Children, made wretched by me, an infortunate Father, and Husband: Tell them, and my Friends, (I intreate you, for Gods cauſe) that if I be (as I ſuſpect I ſhall be) put to Death in <hi>Sherris,</hi> I will dye a Chriſtian Soldier, no way, I hope, diſhonouring my King, Countrey, or the Iuſtice of my Cauſe, or my Religion.</p>
            <p>Anon after, away was I conueyed with a ſtrong Guard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pike</hi> Priſoner in <hi>Sherrys.</hi>
               </note> by the Gouernour of <hi>Cales,</hi> and brought into <hi>Sherrys</hi> on a Thurſeday, about twelue at night.</p>
            <p>On the Sunday following, two Friers were ſent to me, (both of them being <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men, and ſpeaking very good <hi>Engliſh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two Friers ſent to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him.</note>) One of them was caled <hi>Padre Iuan,</hi> (Father <hi>Iohn.</hi>) After a ſad and graue Salutation; Brother (quoth he) I come in Loue to you, and Charity to your Soule, to Confeſſe you: And if to vs, (as your Spirituall Ghoſtly Fathers) you will lay open your Sinnes, wee will forgiue them, and make your way to Heauen, for to morrow you muſt dye.</p>
            <p>I deſired them, that they would giue me a little reſpite, that I might retire into a priuate Chamber, and inſtantly I would repaire to them, and giue them ſatisfaction: Leaue I had; Away I went, and imediately returned: They asked me, if I had yet reſolued, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21327:10"/>
I would come to Confeſsion: I told them, I had been at Confeſsion already: One of them demaunded, with whome? I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with God the Father: And with nobody elſe (ſayd the other?) Yes, (quoth I,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pike</hi> at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, but with no Friers</note>) and with Ieſus Chriſt, my Redeemer, who hath both power and will, to forgiue all Men their Sinnes, that truely Repent; Before theſe Two, haue I falne on my knees, and Confeſt my grieuous offences, and truſt, they will giue me a free Abſolution, and Pardon.</p>
            <p>What thinke you of the Pope? ſayd Father <hi>Iohn:</hi> I anſwered, I knew him not: They, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſhaking their heads, told me, they were ſorry for me, and ſo departed.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus I lay in <hi>Sherrys,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Captaine of the Fort a Priſoner.</note> the Captaine of the Fort <hi>(Don Franciſco Buſtamente)</hi> was brought in, Priſoner for his Life, becauſe he deliuered vp the Caſtle; but whether he dyed for it, or no, I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>My day of Triall being come, I was brought from Priſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duke of</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina, <hi>D. of</hi> Macada,<hi>D.</hi> Ferdinando, Giron, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe</hi> De Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenezes, &amp;c.</note> into the Towne of <hi>Sherrys,</hi> by two Drumbes, and a hundred Shotte, before three Dukes, foure Condes, or Earles, foure Marqueſſes, beſides other great Perſons; the towne hauing in it, at leaſt, fiue thouſand Soldiers.</p>
            <p>At my firſt appearing before the Lordes, my Sword lying before them on a Table, the Duke of <hi>Medina</hi> asked me if I knew that Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon;
<pb facs="tcp:21327:11"/>
It was reached to me; I tooke it, and embraced it in mine armes, and with teares in mine eyes, kiſt the Pomell of it. He then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, how many Men I had kild with that Weapon? I told him, if I had kild One, I had not bene there now, before that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Aſſembly, for when I had him at my foote, begging for Mercy, I gaue him life, yet he, then very poorely, did me a miſchiefe: Then they asked <hi>Don Iohn</hi> (my Priſoner) what Woundes I gaue him; He ſayd, none: Vpon this he was rebuked, and told; That if vpon our firſt Encounter, he had run me through, it had beene a faire and Noble Triumph; but ſo to wound me, being in the hands of others, they held it Baſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſtions by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </note>Then ſayd the Duke of <hi>Medyna</hi> to me; Come on <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man, What Shippe came you in? I told him, The <hi>Conuertine:</hi> Who was your Captaine? Captaine <hi>Portar:</hi> What Ordnance carryed your Shippe? I ſayd, forty Peices. But the Lords looking all this while on a Paper, which they held in their hands: Duke <hi>Medyna</hi> ſayd, In their Note, there was but thirty eight.</p>
            <p>In that Paper (as after I was informed, by my two <hi>Iriſh</hi> Interpreters) there was ſet downe, the Number of our Shippes, their Burden, Men, Munition, Victuall, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp;c. as perfect, as wee our ſelues had
<pb facs="tcp:21327:11"/>
them in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of what Strength (quoth an other Duke) is the Fort at <hi>Plymouth?</hi> I anſwered, very Strong: What Ordnance in it? Fifty ſayd I: That is not ſo, ſayd he, there is but ſeuenteene: How many Soldiers are in the Fort? I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, two hundred: That is not ſo, (quoth a Conde) there is but twenty.</p>
            <p>Marqueſſe <hi>Alquenezes</hi> asked me, Of what ſtrength the little Iland was before <hi>Plymouth?</hi> I told him, I knew not: Then (quoth he) wee doe.</p>
            <p>Is <hi>Plymouth</hi> a Walled Towne? Yes my Lords: And a good Wall? Yes ſayd I, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Wall: True, ſayd a Duke, to leape ouer with a Staffe. And hath the Towne, ſayd the Duke of <hi>Medyna,</hi> ſtrong Gates? Yes: But, quoth he, there was neither Wood nor Iron to thoſe Gates, but two dayes before your Fleete came away.</p>
            <p>Now, before I goe any farther, let me not forget to tell you, that my two <hi>Iriſh</hi> Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, had been heere in <hi>England</hi> the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, &amp; when our Fleete came from <hi>England,</hi> they came for <hi>Spaine;</hi> Hauing ſeene our King at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> when the Soldiers there ſhewed their Armes, and did then diligently obſerue what the King did, and how he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelfe.</p>
            <p>How chance (ſayd Duke <hi>Giron</hi>) did you not
<pb facs="tcp:21327:12"/>
in all this Brauery of the Fleete take <hi>Cales,</hi> as you tooke <hi>Puntall?</hi> I replyed, that the Lord Generall might eaſily haue taken <hi>Cales,</hi> for he had neere a thouſand Scaling Ladders to ſet vp, and a thouſand Men to looſe; but he was loath to rob an Almeshouſe, hauing a better Market to goe to: <hi>Cales,</hi> I told them, was held Poore, Vnmand, and Vnmunitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: What better Market, ſayd <hi>Medyna?</hi> I told him, <hi>Genoa,</hi> or <hi>Lisbone,</hi> and as I heard, there was inſtantly, vpon this, an Army of ſixe thouſand Soldiers ſent to <hi>Lisbone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, quoth one of the Earles, when thou meetſt me in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> wilt thou bid me wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? I modeſtly told him, I could wiſh, they would not too haſtely come to <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> for they ſhould finde it another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of place, then as now they ſleight it.</p>
            <p>Many other Queſtions were put to me by theſe great Dons, which ſo well as God did enable me, I anſwered, they ſpeaking in <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> and their words interpreted to me, by thoſe two <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men before ſpoken of, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo relate my ſeuerall anſwers to the Lords.</p>
            <p>And by the common People, who encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt me round, many ieerings, mockeries, ſcornes, and bitter ieſtes, were to my face throwne vpon our Nation, which I durſt not ſo much as bite my lippe againſt, but with an inforced patient eare ſtood ſtill, and let them
<pb facs="tcp:21327:12"/>
runne on in their Reuilings.</p>
            <p>At the length, amongſt many other repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſpightfull Names, one of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes</hi> called <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men <hi>Gallinas,</hi> (Hennes;) At which, the great Lordes fell a laughing: Herevpon, one of the Dukes (poynting to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Soldiers,) bid me note how their King kept them; And indeed, they were all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous braue in Apparell, Hattes, Bandes, Cuffes, Garters, &amp;c, and ſome of them in Chaines of Gold: And asked farther, If I thought theſe would prooue ſuch <hi>Hennes</hi> as our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> when next yeare they ſhould come into <hi>England?</hi> I ſayd no: But being ſomewhat imboldned by his merry Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I told him as merily, I thought they would be within one degree of <hi>Hennes:</hi> What meanſt thou by that, ſayd a Conde? I reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they would prooue <hi>Pullets,</hi> or <hi>Chickens.</hi> Darſt thou then (quoth Duke <hi>Medyna,</hi> with a brow halfe angry) fight with one of theſe <hi>Spaniſh Pullets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O my Lord, ſayd I, I am a Priſoner, and my Life at Stake, and therefore dare not be ſo bold to aduenture vpon any ſuch Action: There were heere of vs <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſome foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Thouſand, in which Number, there were aboue twelue Thouſand, better, &amp; ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Men then euer I ſhall be; Yet, with the licence of this Princely Aſſembly, I dare ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
<pb facs="tcp:21327:13"/>
the breaking of a Rapier; And withall, told him, Hee was vnworthy the Name of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, that ſhould refuſe to Fight with one Man of any Nation whatſoeuer. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, my Shackells were knockt off, and my Iron Ring and Chayne taken from my Neck.</p>
            <p>Roome was made for the Combatants, Rapier and Dagger the Weapons:<note place="margin">A Fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Peeke,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </note> A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Champion preſents himſelfe, Named <hi>Signior Tiago;</hi> When after wee had played ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable good time, I diſarmed, him as thus.</p>
            <p>I caught his Rapier betwixt the Barres of my Poniard, and there held it, till I cloſed in with him, and tripping vp his Heeles, I tooke his Weapons out of his hands, and deliuered them to the Dukes.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh, that all you, my deere Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men, who reade this Relation, had either bin there, without danger, to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held vs; Or, that He with whome I fought, were heer in Perſon, to iuſtifie the iſſue of that Combat.</p>
            <p>I was then demaunded, If I durſt Fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other? I told them, my heart was good to aduenture; but humbly requeſted them, to giue me pardon, if I refuſed.</p>
            <p>For, to my ſelfe I too well knew, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is Haughty, Impatient of the leaſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front; And when he receiues but a Touch of any Diſhonor, Diſgrace, or Blemiſh, (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:21327:13"/>
in his owne Countrey, and from an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Man,) his Reuenge is implacable, mortall, and bloudy.</p>
            <p>Yet being by the Noblemen, preſſed agen, and agen, to try my Fortune with an other, I (ſeeing my Life in the Lyons paw, to ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with whome for ſafety, there was no way but one, and being afrayd to diſpleaſe them,) ſayd, That if their Graces, and Greatneſſes, would giue me leaue to play at mine Owne Countrey Weapon, called the <hi>Quarter-Staffe,</hi> I was then ready there, an Oppoſite, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Commer, whome they would call foorth; and would willingly lay downe my Life before thoſe Princes, to doe them Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; prouided, my Life might by no foule meanes be taken from me.</p>
            <p>Herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the head of a Halbert, which went with a Screw, was taken off, and the Steall deliuered to me; the other But-end of the Staffe hauing a ſhort Iron Pike in it: This was my Armor, and in my place I ſtood, expecting an Opponent.</p>
            <p>At the laſt,<note place="margin">The Quarter-Staffe againſt three Rapiers.</note> a hanſome and well Spirited <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſteps foorth, with his Rapier and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard: They asked me, what I ſayd to Him? I told them, I had a ſure Friend in my hand, that neuer failed me, and therefore made little account of that One to play with, and ſhould ſhew them no Sport.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:14"/>Then, a Second (Arm'd as before) preſents himſelfe: I demanded, if there would come no more? The Dukes asked, how many I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired? I told them, any number vnder Sixe: Which reſolution of mine, they ſmiling at, in a kind of ſcorne, held it not Manly, (it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,) nor fit for their owne Honors, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Nation, to worry one Man with a Multitude; and therefore appointed Three onely, (ſo Weapond) to enter into the Liſtes.</p>
            <p>Now Gentlemen, if here you condemne mee, for plucking (with mine owne hands) ſuch an aſſured danger, vpon mine owne head; Accept of theſe Reaſons for excuſe.</p>
            <p>To dye, I thought it moſt certaine, but to dye baſely, I would not: For Three to kill One, had bin to Mee no Diſhonor; To Them (Weapons conſidered,) no Glory; An Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Subiection, I eſteemed better, then an Ignoble Conqueſt. Vpon theſe Thoughts, I fell to it.</p>
            <p>The Rapier Men trauerſt their ground, I, mine; Dangerous Thruſts were put in, and with dangerous hazard auoyded: Showtes ecchoed to Heauen, to encourage the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards;</hi> Not a ſhoute, nor Hand, to hearten the poore <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man; Onely, Heauen I had in mine Eye, the Honor of my Countrey in my Heart, my Fame at the Stake, my Life on a narrow Bridge, and Death both before me
<pb facs="tcp:21327:14"/>
and behind me.</p>
            <p>It was not now a time to dally, they ſtill made full at me; And I had beene a Coward to my Selfe, and a Villane to my Nation, if I had not called vp all that weake Manhood which was mine, to guard my owne Life, and ouerthrow my Enemies.</p>
            <p>Plucking vp therefore a good heart, ſeeing my ſelfe faint and wearied, I vowed to my Soule, to doe ſomething, ere ſhe departed from me: And ſo ſetting All vpon One Caſt, It was my Good Fortune (it was my God did it for Mee) with the But-end where the Iron Pike was, to Kill one of the Three; and within a few Boutes after, to Diſarme the other two, cauſing the One of them to fly into the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Soldiers then preſent, and the Other for refuge fled behind the Bench.</p>
            <p>I hope, if the brauing <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſet vpon <hi>England</hi> (as they threaten,) we ſhall euery One of vs, giue the repulſe to more then Three; Of which good Iſſue for the Publique, I take this my Priuate ſucceſſe to be a Pledge.</p>
            <p>Now was I in greater Danger, being (as I thought) in Peace, then before, when I was in Battaile: For, a generall Murmure filled the Ayre, with Threatnings at me; the Soldiers eſpecially bit their thumbes, and how was it poſſible for me to ſcape?</p>
            <p>Which, the Noble Duke of <hi>Medina Sidenia</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:15"/>
ſeeing, called me to him, and inſtantly cauſed Proclamation to be made,<note place="margin">The braue minde of <hi>Medina.</hi>
               </note> that none, on paine of death, ſhould meddle with mee; And by his Honorable Protection, I got off; And not off, onely with Safety, but with Money. For by the Dukes and Condes, were giuen me in Gold, to the value of foure Pounds tenne Shillings ſterling; and by the Marqueſſe <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenezes</hi> himſelfe, as much; He embracing me in his Armes, and beſtowing vpon me, that long <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ruſſet Cloake I now weare, which he tooke from one of his Mens backs; And withall, furniſhed me with a cleane Band and Cuffes; It being one of the greateſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lord can doe to a meane Man, to reward him with ſome Garment, as recompence of Merrit.</p>
            <p>After our Fight in <hi>Sherris,</hi> I was kept in the Marqueſſe <hi>Alquenezes</hi> Houſe, who one day (out of his Noble affability) was pleaſant in ſpeech with me; And by my Interpreter, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I would Sing: I willing to obey him (whoſe goodneſſe I had taſted,) did ſo, and ſung this Pſalme: <hi>When as we ſate in Babilon, &amp;c.</hi> The meaning of which being told, he ſaide to me, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, comfort thy ſelfe, for thou art in no Captiuity.</p>
            <p>After this, I was ſent to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> lying at <hi>Madrill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peeke</hi> ſent to the K ng at <hi>Madrill.</hi>
               </note> My Conduct being foure Gentlemen of the Marqueſſe <hi>Alquenezes;</hi> He
<pb facs="tcp:21327:15"/>
allowing vnto me, in the Iourney, twenty Shillings a day when wee Trauelled, and ten Shillings a day when we lay ſtill.</p>
            <p>At my being in <hi>Madrill,</hi> before I ſaw the King; My Entertainement (by the Marqueſſe <hi>Alquenezes</hi> appointment,) was at his owne Houſe, where I was lodged in the moſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Bedde that euer I beheld; and had from his Noble Lady, a Welcome farre aboue my poore deſeruing but worthy the Greatneſſe of ſo excellent a Woman; She beſtowing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, whilſt I lay in her Houſe a very faire <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Shirt, richly Laced, and at my parting from <hi>Madrill,</hi> a Chayne of Gold, and two Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells for my Wife, and other pretty Thinges for my Children.</p>
            <p>And now that her Noble Courteſies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with my owne Thankefullnes,<note place="margin">A Noble <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Lady.</note> leade me to ſpeake of this Honorable <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady; I might very iuſtly be condemned of Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, if I ſhould not remember, with like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, another rare Patterne of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine goodnes, to me, a diſtreſſed, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Stranger: And that was, the Lady of <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Cales;</hi> She,<note place="margin">Another.</note> out of a Reſpect ſhe bare me, for ſauing her Husbands Life, came along with him to <hi>Sherrys,</hi> He being there to giue in Euidence againſt me; And as before, when I lay Priſoner in <hi>Cales,</hi> ſo in <hi>Sherrys,</hi> ſhe often relieued me with Money, and other Meanes;
<pb facs="tcp:21327:16"/>
My Duty and Thankes euer wayte vpon them Both.</p>
            <p>Vpon <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> I was Preſented to the King, the Queene, and <hi>Don Carolo</hi> the <hi>Infante.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being brought before him, I fell (as it was fitt) on my Knees: Many Queſtions were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me, which ſo well as my plaine witte directed me, I reſolued.</p>
            <p>In the end, his Maieſty offered me a Yearely Pention, (to a good Vallew) if I would Serue him, eyther at Land or at Sea; For which his Royall Fauors, I confeſſing my ſelfe infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bound, and my Life indebted to his Mercy, moſt humbly intreated, that with his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Leaue, I might be ſuffered to returne into mine owne Countrey, being a Subiect onely to the King of <hi>England,</hi> my Souereigne.</p>
            <p>And beſides that Bond of Allegiance, there was another Obligation, due from me, to a Wife and Children; And therefore, moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiuely beg'd, that his Maieſty would be ſo Princely minded, as to pitty my Eſtate, and to let me goe: To which he at laſt granted; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing vpon me, one hundred Piſtoletts, to beare my Charges.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus left <hi>Spaine,</hi> I tooke my way through ſome part of <hi>France;</hi> Where, by occaſion, happening into Company of ſeuen <hi>Spaniards,</hi> their Tongues were too lauiſh in
<pb facs="tcp:21327:16"/>
Speeches againſt our Nation; Vpon which, ſome high words flying vp and downe the Roome, I leaped from the Table, and drew.</p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did the like (none of the reſt being Weaponed, which was more then I knew.)</p>
            <p>Vpon the noiſe of this Buſtling, two <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Men more came in, Who vnderſtanding the Abuſes offered to our Countrey, the (<hi>Spaniards</hi> in a ſhort time, Recanted on their Knees) their Raſhneſſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo hoyſing Saile for <hi>England;</hi> I Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the three and twenty day of Aprill, 1626. at <hi>Foy</hi> in <hi>Cornewall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus endeth my <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pilgrimage: With thankes to my good God, that in this extraordinany Manner preſerued me, amidſt theſe deſperate Dangers.</p>
            <p>Therefore moſt gratious God, (Defender of Men abroad, and Protector of them at home,) How am I bounden to thy Diuine Maieſtie, for thy manifold Mercies?</p>
            <p>On my Knees I thanke thee, with my Tongue I will praiſe thee, with my Handes Fight in thy Quarrell, and all the daies of my Life ſerue thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:17"/>Out of the Red-Sea, I haue eſcaped; From the Lyons Den, bin deliuered; I reſcued from Death, and ſnatcht out of the Iawes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, onely by Thee, O my God; Glory be to thy Name, for euer, and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:17"/>
            <head>Certaine Verſes, VVritten by a Friend, in Comendations of the Author <hi>Richard Peeke.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SEldome doe Clowdes ſo dimne the day,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Sol</hi> will once his Beames diſplay:</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Neptune</hi> driues the ſurging Seas,</l>
               <l>Sometimes he giues them quiet eaſe;</l>
               <l>And ſo few Proiects ſpeed ſo ill,</l>
               <l>But ſomewhat chaunceth at our will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I will not inſtance in the Great,</l>
               <l>Placed in Honors higher Seate;</l>
               <l>Though Vertue in a Noble Line</l>
               <l>Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the more doth ſhine:</l>
               <l>Yet this is procu'd by Sword and Pen,</l>
               <l>Deſert oft dwells in priuate Men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My proofe is not farre hence to ſeeke,</l>
               <l>There is at hand braue <hi>Richard Peeke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe worth his Foes cannot reuoke,</l>
               <l>Borne in the Towne of <hi>Tauyſtoke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Deuon,</hi> where <hi>Minerua</hi> ſitts</l>
               <l>Shaping ſtoute Hearts, and pregnant Witts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:18"/>
               <l>This well reſolu'd and hardy Sparke,</l>
               <l>Ayming at Fame, as at a Marke,</l>
               <l>Was not compell'd againſt his will,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Mars</hi> his field to try his skill:</l>
               <l>As Voluntary he did goe,</l>
               <l>To ſerue his King againſt his Foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If he had pleas'd, he might haue ſpent</l>
               <l>His daies at home, in ſafe content:</l>
               <l>But nurcing Valour in his breſt,</l>
               <l>He would aduenture with the Beſt,</l>
               <l>Willing to ſhed his deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>To doe his Prince, and Countrey good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus bent, he adding Winges to Feete,</l>
               <l>Departed with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleete:</l>
               <l>There was no rub, nor ſtay at all,</l>
               <l>The Shipps ſaild with a pleaſant Gale:</l>
               <l>In ſetting forth they by their hap,</l>
               <l>Seem'd lul'd in <hi>Amphitrites</hi> lap.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At length they did arriue at <hi>Cales,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where reſtles <hi>Peeke</hi> againſt the Walles</l>
               <l>Made foureſccore Shot towards the Shore,</l>
               <l>Making the Welkyn wide to rore:</l>
               <l>He kept his ſtanding in this ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Setting a ſtraw by loſſe of life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Into a Vineyard afterward</l>
               <l>He marcht, and ſtood vpon his guard;</l>
               <l>There he an Horſe-man did diſmount,</l>
               <l>By outward port of good account:</l>
               <l>But did on him compasſion take,</l>
               <l>And ſpar'd his life for pitties ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:18"/>
               <l>The next aſſault, vneuen he felt,</l>
               <l>For with twelue <hi>Spaniards</hi> he dealt</l>
               <l>At once, and held them luſty play,</l>
               <l>Vntill through odds, theirs was the day:</l>
               <l>From eare to eare they pearc'd his head,</l>
               <l>And to the Towne him Captiue led.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Priſon they him ſhut by night,</l>
               <l>Loaden with Chaines of greiuous waight,</l>
               <l>All comfortleſſe in Dungion deepe,</l>
               <l>Where Stench annoyes, and Vermines creepe:</l>
               <l>He grouel'd in this loathſome Cell,</l>
               <l>Where gaſtly frights and horrors dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet nothing could his courage quaile,</l>
               <l>Hunger, nor thirſt, nor wound, nor Iayle:</l>
               <l>For being brought before a <hi>Don,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And askt, Why <hi>England</hi> did ſet on</l>
               <l>A ſcraping, not a pecking <hi>Hen?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He anſwer'd, ſtaine not <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That <hi>England</hi> is a Nation ſtoute,</l>
               <l>And till the laſt will fight it out:</l>
               <l>My ſelfe could prooue by Chiualrie,</l>
               <l>If for a Captiue this were free:</l>
               <l>Why, (quoth the Duke) darſt thou to fight</l>
               <l>With any of my Men in fight?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of thouſands whom in Warre you vſe,</l>
               <l>Not one (quoth <hi>Peeke</hi>) doe I refuſe:</l>
               <l>A choſen Champion then there came,</l>
               <l>Whoſe heeles he tript, as at a game,</l>
               <l>And from his Hand his Rapier tooke,</l>
               <l>Preſenting it vnto the Duke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21327:19"/>
               <l>Then three at once did him oppoſe,</l>
               <l>They Rapiers, he a long Staffe choſe,</l>
               <l>The vſe whereof ſo well he knowes,</l>
               <l>He conquerd them with nimble blowes:</l>
               <l>One that beſide him playd his round,</l>
               <l>He threw as dead vnto the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Noble Duke who this did ſee,</l>
               <l>Commended <hi>Peeke,</hi> and ſet him free;</l>
               <l>He gaue him Guifts, and did commaund</l>
               <l>That none ſhould wrong him in their Land;</l>
               <l>So well he did him entertayne,</l>
               <l>And ſent him to the Court of <hi>Spayne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There he was fed with no worſe meate,</l>
               <l>Then which the King himſelfe did eate;</l>
               <l>His Lodging rich, for he did lie</l>
               <l>In furniture of Tapeſtrie:</l>
               <l>The King what of him he had heard,</l>
               <l>Did with his Treaſure well reward.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our then Ambaſſador was there,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peekes</hi> Pike and praiſe he doth declare:</l>
               <l>At <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court whiles he attends,</l>
               <l>He thriues for Vertues ſake: as Friends</l>
               <l>Foes ſent him in triumphant ſort</l>
               <l>Home from a Foe and Forreigne Port.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thus his very Foes him lou'd,</l>
               <l>And Deeds againſt themſelues aproou'd;</l>
               <l>How ſhould his Friends his loue embrace,</l>
               <l>And yeild him countenance and grace?</l>
               <l>The praiſe and worth how can we cloke</l>
               <l>Of manly <hi>Peeke</hi> of <hi>Tauyſtoke?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21327:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
